The last section of this chapter deals with embolism,
and embolism is technically defined as an intravascular mass
that travels through the bloodstream
and then occludes a blood vessel.
And so this is the technical definition of embolism.
And, of course, the symptoms are going to depend
on the blood vessel that is involved.
Now, the reason why I have this in this chapter
is because the most common source of embolism
is actually a thrombus, and that's called a thromboembolist.
So the patient gets a thrombus.
The thrombus breaks away and then floats down the bloodstream
and then lodges someplace else.
That's called a thromboembolist.
And, again, this is the most common type of embolist,
and so, therefore, I place this discussion
at the end of this chapter.
Another type of embolist that can occur
is called an atherosclerotic embolist.
And the idea here is that the patient has atherosclerosis.
So imagine that there's an atherosclerotic plaque
here in the blood vessel,
and a piece of this atherosclerotic plaque breaks off
and then travels down the blood vessel
and then lodges someplace else.
So that's called an atherosclerotic embolist.
And, again, it's due to dislodging of a plaque.
And when you look at the embolist,
the way by which you know that it arose from atherosclerosis
or that it's a piece of atherosclerosis, essentially,
is that you'll see cholesterol clefts in the embolist.
And that's key, cholesterol clefts in the embolist.
So here's a picture.
This is a blood vessel.
And you can see that this blood vessel is occluded here
by this embolist.
And when we look at this embolist,
one of the things that we recognize
is that there are these cholesterol crystals
here in the middle of it,
indicating that this must have arisen from atherosclerosis
that dislodged and then traveled down the bloodstream
to occlude the blood supply.
Another type of embolist that we can have is a fat embolist.
And this is where you would crack open a bone, for example.
So it's classically associated with trauma and bone fracture
or soft tissue could get damaged.
This would release fat into the blood supply,
which could then lodge someplace else.
Now, this classically develops while there is a fracture.
So the patient gets a fracture
and then shortly thereafter gets a fat embolist
or shortly after repair of a fracture.
So, you know, within a short period of time after repair.
The classic findings are that the patient has dyspnea
along with petechia on the skin overlying the chest.
And the reason they get dyspnea is because the classic location
for a fat embolist is the blood vessels of the lung.
So the fat basically goes to the blood vessels of the lung
and then gets lodged in those blood vessels.
Here's a classic picture of a fat embolist.
Clearly, this is a blood vessel here.
This center area represents the lumen of the blood vessel.
And we can see that this lumen is occluded
by all these circular spaces, which basically represent fat.
So this would be an example of a fat embolist.
Another type of embolist that can arise within the bloodstream
is called a gas embolist.
This is classically seen in something called decompression sickness.
Now, the idea here is that a person goes diving.
And when they go diving, you know that the pressure as they dive,
it increases as the lower they go.
So as they slowly descend, there's increased pressure
and that forces nitrogen to dissolve in the blood.
Now, when the diver comes up, they rapidly ascend.
And when they rapidly ascend, the nitrogen can actually precipitate
out of the blood as small little gas bubbles,
which can then lodge in various tissues,
creating problems of the gas embolist.
So, for example, patients can get joint and muscle pain
because the nitrogen bubbles would lodge within the joints and the muscles.
And also, the nitrogen gas can embolize to the lung,
giving the patient respiratory symptoms.
And when the patient has joint and muscle pain,
that's classically called the BENS, B-E-N-D-S.
And when they have respiratory symptoms,
that's classically called the CHOKES, C-H-O-K-E-S.
Now, there's a chronic form of this disease called Kaysan's disease
in which patients have chronic gas emboli due to nitrogen.
And in this particular case,
those gas emboli would cause infarction of the bone.
And so they get multifocal ischemic necrosis of the bone.
And that's called Kaysan's disease.
Gas emboli can also arise when a patient undergoes laparoscopic surgery.
Remember that during laparoscopic surgery,
we pump air into the abdomen,
and it's possible that some of that air could get into the bloodstream
and then subsequently result in an embolus.
The next type of embolus is called an amniotic fluid embolus.
Obviously, this would be a woman who's pregnant.
The amniotic fluid enters a maternal circulation
and then lodges within the mom's lungs most often.
Usually, this occurs during delivery or during labor.
As I've stated here in your text,
the classic presentation is that of shortness of breath.
That's because you get the emboli within the lung.
You get neurologic symptoms because of the emboli going to the brain.
And the patients also get DIC.
And remember that the amniotic fluid is loaded with tissue thromboplastin.
That's high yield.
The amniotic fluid is loaded with tissue thromboplastin.
And tissue thromboplastin has the ability to activate the coag cascade,
which can then result in DIC.
When you look at the emboli in the patient's lungs,
so you're looking at mom's lung and you notice that there are emboli there,
the characteristic finding in those emboli will be squamous cells and keratin debris.
And the idea here is that remember that the baby was floating around in the amniotic fluid,
and so the baby's skin was sloughing off over time in that amniotic fluid,
and the amniotic fluid will therefore be loaded with squamous cells and keratin debris.
And this is what it looks like.
Here is an alveolar air sac, and this is the interstitium with a blood vessel.
And we can clearly see that within this circular space of the blood vessel,
there is all this keratin debris.
And so when a patient has this keratin debris within the blood vessels,
we think about an amniotic fluid embolus.
One disorder that can arise with embolus is called pulmonary embolus,
and this is usually due to a thromboembolus that arises from a DVT.
Now the idea here is that a patient gets a deep vein thrombosis,
for example, usually of the lower extremity,
usually involving the femoral, iliac, or popliteal veins,
and that deep vein thrombosis can actually dislodge,
and when it dislodges, you'd get a thromboembolus,
and that thromboembolus would eventually enter the pulmonary circulation,
and when it enters the pulmonary circulation,
it can cause something called a pulmonary embolus.
Now most often, when patients get pulmonary embolus, or PE,
it's clinically silent, and that's for two reasons.
Number one, the lung has a dual blood supply.
Remember that the pulmonary artery is going into the lung,
so that's one blood supply,
and then you've also got the bronchial artery coming off the aorta
that also goes to the lung,
which essentially keeps the lung tissue alive and healthy,
and so that's a second blood supply.
So even if you were to occlude a small area of the lung,
the second blood supply would be able to sustain the lung.
So that's one reason why PE is usually clinically silent.
Another reason why PE is clinically silent
is because most emboli are usually small,
and as soon as the embolus lodges within the lung,
it self-resolves and gets lysed.
So these are the two reasons why PE is most often clinically silent.
It is possible, however, as a complication of PE,
to get an area of infarction within the lung.
That's usually going to occur when you have a couple things.
Number one, you need obstruction of a large or medium-sized artery.
So that's really the first thing we need.
You've got to have a big embolus that's going to obstruct
either a large or medium-sized artery.
And number two, the patient needs to have
some sort of pre-existing cardiopulmonary compromise.
Now by having pre-existing cardiopulmonary compromise,
the lung is susceptible to this type of damage,
and therefore having the dual blood supply
would not be as protective as it would be in a normal individual.
So again, two things before you're going to see infarction.
You're going to need a large embolus,
and it's usually going to be a patient
with pre-existing cardiopulmonary compromise.
Only about 10% of PEs actually cause pulmonary infarction.
Clinically, when patients get pulmonary infarction,
then they're going to present with classic signs
of shortness of breath, hemoptysis, pleuritic chest pain,
pleural effusion.
So these are some of the signs and symptoms
that alert us that we might be dealing
with a pulmonary infarction due to a PE.
A VQ scan would show mismatch.
Remember that the V represents ventilation
and the Q represents perfusion.
And of course, if we block the blood supply with a PE,
then the perfusion is going to be abnormal.
At the same time, one of the tests that's useful
is something called a spiral CT,
and the spiral CT would show
that there was a vascular filling defect in the lung,
indicating that we've got some sort of embolus
that's blocking the blood supply within the lung.
Additionally, you can do a Doppler ultrasound
to the lower extremity,
and that would help to identify the source.
It would help you to identify that a DVT is present.
And finally, the D-dimer is going to be elevated.
And the reason why the D-dimer is elevated
is because the patient's lysing both the PE
as well as the DVT,
and so that usually is going to elevate the D-dimer.
Because remember, any time you cut up
a platelet fibrin thrombus,
that's going to result in D-dimer
being pushed out into the blood.
So the D-dimer is often elevated.
On gross exam, when you have a pulmonary infarction,
you classically see a hemorrhagic wedge-shaped infarct.
Now, the reason why you see a wedge-shaped infarct
is the following.
Remember that the blood supply in the lung
is dichotomously branching,
so that if this is the blood supply going this way,
it branches, and then it branches again,
and then it branches again.
And so if you get a PE here,
you're going to get infarction of everything
that would go through this branch and this branch,
which would then knock out this entire area.
And so you can see that this kind of looks like a wedge.
And we say that the wedge points to the area of occlusion.
So that's the reason why the infarction
would be wedge-shaped.
At the same time, the reason why it's hemorrhagic
is because you have a second blood supply
bringing blood into the dead tissue,
and the dead tissue is loose.
And remember that if you go back to Chapter 1
in our discussion of infarction,
we said that in order to get a hemorrhagic infarction,
you need two things.
You need blood to re-enter the dead tissue,
and you need the dead tissue to have a loose consistency
so that it can hold the blood
to reveal a hemorrhagic infarction.
And that's exactly what occurs in the lung.
You've got a second blood supply,
and you've got a loosely organized tissue.
Another possibility of a PE
is that the patient develops sudden death.
This is usually not seen unless you have a massive embolus.
And the classic is a large saddle embolus.
Now the reason why death occurs
is because there is electromechanical dissociation.
So the heart's pumping,
but the blood supply is totally blocked.
And so the patient undergoes sudden death.
And so this is what it classically looks like.
This is a saddle embolus,
and we can see here that
this is the branching of the pulmonary artery,
here and here.
And then we can see that this embolus,
as I'm drawing here,
has saddled and knocked out
both of the pulmonary arteries.
And so there's basically,
and the entire vascular supply is occluded,
and so the heart's going to pump against that,
but blood's not going to be able to go any further.
And so this is an example of a saddle embolus,
and would classically be seen
in a patient who undergoes sudden death.
One final complication,
or final consequence, I should say,
of pulmonary emboli
is that if you have chronic emboli
over a long period of time,
those emboli can be reorganized,
and when they're reorganized,
the patients develop pulmonary hypertension.
So pulmonary hypertension,
which would be high blood pressure
in the pulmonary circuit,
is a complication of chronic emboli
that get reorganized over time.
Now it is also possible
for emboli to lodge in the systemic circuit,
and when they lodge in the systemic circuit,
the most common source
is usually a thromboembolus,
and that usually comes from the left heart.
So when you get systemic emboli,
that is, emboli that shoot off
and lodge someplace in the systemic circuit,
again, the most common source
is a thromboembolus from the left heart.
These will travel down the systemic circuit
to occlude flow to organs.
The most common site is the lower extremities.
And with that,
we conclude our section on embolism,
and that also concludes this chapter.